你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎回到PWN学院
welcome back to pwn college
我是Yan
I'm Yan
今天要讲的是内存中的竞争条件
Today we're going to be talking about race in memories
它是PWN学院竞争条件模块的一部分
part of the race condition module of pwn college
我们已经讨论过文件系统中的竞争条件
we've previously covered races on the file system
那自然有一个问题
and of course a natural question it would be
文件系统之外是否存在竞争条件
can there be races outside of the file system
在其他地方
so in other places
答案是肯定的
and of course the answer is yes
文件系统是出现竞争条件的常见位置
the file system is a very common place to have race conditions
因为它是进程间的共享资源
because it's a shared resource between processes
现在学过了线程
but as we have now Learned about threads
我们知道了内存是线程间的共享资源
we can realize that memory is a shared resource between threads
很明显，既然是共享资源
and obviously since it's a shared resource
多个线程可能会同时使用它
that multiple different threads can use at the same time
如果不多加小心
if extreme care is not taken
内存中就会发生竞争条件
race conditions will arise and do arise in memory
看看这个例子
take a look at this example
这是一个明显的竞态条件
this is a very straightforward race condition
在这个进程中有两个线程
we have two threads in this process
主线程和分配器线程
the main thread and the allocator thread
主线程循环从标准输入读取size变量
the main thread will loop read a size variable
读取1字节
right just one byte
分配器线程循环调用read_data
and the allocator thread will loop and call read_data
read_data会检查
of course read_data will check if the size variable
主线程负责从标准输入读取的size变量
that the main thread is responsible for reading
是否小于16
if size is less than 16
如果size小于16
那么
then
就从标准输入读数据到一个16B大小的栈缓冲区
we will read into a buffer on the stack of size 16
size代表要输入多少字节
how many bytes are indicated by size
现在
now
当然要是没漏洞，我就不展示它了
I wouldn't be showing this example if it wasn't vulnerable
它肯定是有漏洞的
so of course it is vulnerable
它存在TOCTOU漏洞
this is in fact a time of check to time of use vulnerability
与文件系统中讲的一样，只是这发生在内存中
exactly in the style of a file system one just in memory
因为主线程可以修改size变量
why because the main thread can update the size variable
而且就在分配器线程检查和使用之间
while between the time  that allocator thread checks it and uses it
TOCTOU 无疑
time of check time of use boom
让我们看看这里发生了什么
let's take a look at what happens here
好吧
alright
所以
so
我实现了这个pthread_race
I implemented this of course  pthread_race
就是这个
here it is
和ppt上的相同
exactly what's on the slide
编译它
if we compile it
pthread_race pthread_race.c
链接pthread库
linking pthread boom
运行它
alright and we run it
打错了
oops wrong 1 apologies
当然最开始输出的size是42
it of course starts out with that size of 42
看这里，初始值是42
that's just in the initial size right there
按一下回车，会怎样？
all right so let's see what happens if I hit enter
回车是十六进制0xa，即10
that's enter of course is Hex 10
所以它要求我发送10个字节（的数据）
and so now it's asking me to send 10 bytes
我发送10个字节
I send 10 bytes
然后它接着要10字节
and then it keeps asking for 10 bytes
我可以发送更多字节
I can send more
然后报 size 49 无效
then says invalid size 49
最后还问我要10个字节
eventually ask me 10 bytes again
为什么它又问我要10个字节
why did it ask me 10 bytes again
因为我按了回车
because when I hit enter
在这一长串1后面跟了一个0xa
after all of these ones I sent along another 0xa
即10，或者说是一个换行符
another 10, a new line all right
所以这里有点奇怪
so there's some weirdness going on here
一方面
for one thing
它让我输入10个字节，但是
it asked me to input 10 bytes but
但实际上我输入了一堆
actually put a bunch
所以对于这些多的字节
so for each one of these
每个字节都应该被读入，报错：非法size
it should have read it in  and said oh this is an invalid size
但这里只报了一次错。为什么？
but only said it once why
因为这些线程没有同步好
because of course these threads are not synchronized in any way
所以估计是这样的
so what probably happened or what certainly happened is
这里对size的检查或者读取发生了很多次
this check or this read of the size variable happened many many many times
而 read_data 只执行了一次
while this only happened to execute once
内核决定如何调度不同的线程
it's up to the kernel how to schedule different threads
不由我们决定
not up to us
原理就是这么个原理
so that is what happens
那我们该如何利用这一点呢
all right so how do we exploit this well
很容易
very easily
基本上就是一直给它灌数据
basically we shove data at it
直到触发TOCTOU
until we trigger that time of check time of use
具体来说
and
哦，出了点问题
oops I don't know what happened there
直到在这里检查时size小于16
until size is smaller than 16 here
但在这里使用时大于16
and bigger than 16 here
当然，会让它读入一个很大的数
and then of course it will read some giant numer
一个简单的方法是
an easy way to do this is
在循环中输出1和ff
just in a loop echo a 1 byte  and then an FF byte
持续输出
just in a loop
这会输出大量数据
okay this will just give us quite a lot of data random data
再通过管道传给pthread_race
but if you pipe this in to our pthread_race
就成了
boom
只循环了几次
goes a couple of times
它读入了0xff，报了非法大小
it read the hex FF the invalid size
它首先读取1
it first read the 1
但是在它读取1
but in between it reading the 1
和分配器线程实际检查size之间
and the actual size check in the allocators thread actually happening
它已经读入FF了
it already went on to read this FF right
持续了3次
and then it went on until
终于1被读入到size
the one got read into size
且通过了检查
that passed the check
让我把代码调出来
let me bring up
是这样子的
all right so what happened here
显然这里读入的size是255（ff）
obviously we read in a size of 255 here
然后这个线程可能运行了3次
and then maybe this thread ran 3 times
然后这个线程运行了一次
and the time it took this thread to run once
在它的循环中这是很有可能的
that's very possible through its loop
这完全取决于内核调度的细节
it all depends on the specifics of kernel scheduling
也可能主线程运行多次
or maybe this thread kept running a lot
恰巧分配器线程运行了3次，且3次size都是ff
and we just got chance that this thread ran while the size variable was 255 three times
这也是可能的情形
that's the likely scenario
最终
then eventually
这里执行size检查时，它是1
this thread looped through the size check when the size was 1
执行到这里时，大小仍然是1
and by the time it got to here the size was still 1
也是很有可能的
very possible
它只向buff中读入了1字节
it only read one byte into the buffer
好的，最后得到了一个合法的size 1
and then eventually we got a valid size of one byte
所以这里读入了1字节的size
so this ran read size of one byte
这里的检查也通过了
then this check passed
输出没报错
it printed great job
然后主线程读入255到size中
then this ran and read in 255 in the main thread
又切回分配器线程
and in the allocator thread
它原以为要读入1字节，但此时实际读入255字节
this guy ran and read in 255 bytes where he thought it was reading in one byte
当然就破环了栈
and of course we smashed the stack
这是一个典型的内存中的竞争条件
alright there's a very typical data race in memory
导致了很多漏洞
causes many many vulnerabilities
它实际上很难对付
and it's actually very hard to deal with
它是一个厉害的漏洞
right this is a real deal vulnerability
它特殊在
a special case of this vulnerability is that
它可能出现在用户态和内核态切换的过程中
it can arise between the userland and the kernel
显然，这令他有很大的危害
obviously this makes it much much more impactful right
还记得内核函数copy_from_user吗
remember the kernel function copy_from_user from the kernel module
它从用户获取输入
it takes input from the user
从用户空间复制
and it copies it from user space
复制到内核空间
it copies it into kernel space
有时候开发者会犯
sometimes developers make mistakes that are basically
内核与用户空间之间的TOCTOU
time of chuck time of use vulnerabilities between the kernel and the user space
看一下这个情况
look at this situation
有一个ioctl处理程序接收user_buffer
you have an ioctl handler that takes a user_buffer
它是一个用户空间地址的指针，用作ioctl的参数
of a pointer to buffer in user space as the ioctl argument right
它调用check_safety检查user_buffer
it calls check_safety on the user_buffer
检查一下，确保这个user_buffer
and says hey check to make sure that this user_buffer
中的size小于16
the size encoded in it is less than 16
为此，它从用户空间地址复制size
to do that it copies the size from the user
然后将其与16进行比较
and then it compares it against the maximum size
然后返回
and returns that right
当然
of course
我忘了写if语句了
I forgot to put an if statement there
稍等一下
let me just one second
好了，看起来好多了
all right that looks a little better
我们在这里做了安全校验
so we do this safety check
但在这里我们又从用户空间中获取size
but then we grab the size again from user space
这里是检查的时候
right of course this is the time of check
这里使用的时候
this is the time of use
就在检查和使用之间
between the time of check and the time of use
用户空间中的值可以被修改
the value in user space can be changed
当然不是调用ioctl的线程
of course not by the thread that called ioctl
这是一个ioctl处理程序
this is an ioctl handler
因此调用ioctl的线程已被挂起
so the thread that called ioctl is suspended
但在同一进程中它可能有兄弟线程
but it could have a sibling thread in that same process
它可以访问用户空间中的内存
that has access to this memory space in user space
并且可以在检查和使用之间改变这个值
and could change that value between our time of check and our time of use
在第一次从用户空间取值
between the first fetch from user space
和第二次从用户空间取值之间
and the second fetch from user space
这被称为双重获取漏洞
this is called a double fetch vulnerability
它在今天仍然猖獗
it runs rampant even today
这是一个大问题
and it is a big problem
因为，如果这个size突然增大
because obviously if this size is suddenly increased
我们就可以在内核中溢出这个缓冲区
we can overflow this buffer in the kernel
如果认为让攻击者控制用户态执行流够糟了
and if you think that having an attacker control execution user space is bad
等以后看到它发生在内核态，你会体会到它的危害
just wait until you see what happens in the kernel
这在之后的视频会讲
and you will see what happens in the kernel in toddler 2
好吧
all right
其他数据竞争
other data race concepts right
数据竞争可能会有非常奇怪的影响，即使
data races can have really weird effects even if
不一定非得是TOCTOU
they are not necessarily time of check time of use
好的
right
看看这个例子
look at this situation for example
有两个线程
we have two threads that
每次num都先自增再自减
each increment and then decrement a numer
不出意外的话
if the world made sense
当执行到这里，num总是0
you would expect this num to always be zero by the time this line comes around
因为先自增再自减
because there's an increment a decrement
这里我们只在非零的情况下输出
and here we printed out only if it's non zero
按理说它永远不会打印出来
you'd expect it never be printed out
好的，我们看看实际是怎样的
right but let me show you what in reality happens
有一个pthread_clober
so we have pthread_clobber
和ppt上的代码一样
same code as you saw on the slide
Num + + Num - -
num plus plus num minus minus
如果num不为零，就输出
and if num is not zero it printed out
已经编译好了，运行它
already compiled it so let's just run it
可以看到NUM是1
and you can see NUM is one
这有点奇怪
that's weird
但这也说得通
right but it kind of makes sense
可能因为线程不同步的原因
you might have a desync between those two threads
但它会继续增长
but then it keeps going
怎么可能是5呢
how can it possibly be 5
即使他们不同步
even if they desynced
一个线程自增了
and one thread incremented
同时另一个线程打印了它
as the other thread was printing it out
也应该是1
that should be a 1
然后它会再次自减
and then it would be decremented again
但现在都到15了
but now we're up to 15 over here
这太疯狂了
this is crazy
这应该是不可能的，但确实发生了
this shouldn't be possible but it is
这怎么可能?
how is it possible
有可能执行了这个指令序列
it is possible with this sample way of scheduling the instructions
再次强调，线程调度顺序是不确定的
and again threads are scheduled nondeterministically
除非你主动控制
unless you explicitly take over their scheduling
我马上会讲到怎么做
I'll talk about how in a second
但
but
我们先看这个执行顺序
if we trace through this scheduling
有2个线程自增了
you have the two threads for the increment
T1执行完了自增操作
first thread one runs all the way through the increment
读取并自增了num
so reading the numer incrementing the numer
将num从内存读入寄存器
reading the memory where numer resides into a register
寄存器自增
incrementing the register
然后写回内存
and writing it back out
最后得到num = 1
we end up with num being equal to 1
T2也执行完了自增操作
thread two runs increments it
Num=2
num equal to 2
但自减时2个线程是交错的
and now the decrement part is interleaved
读入到寄存器的都是2
and so they both read in two
都从2自减，最后都是1（线程有单独的寄存器上下文）
they both decrement 2 so they both end up with 1
然后它们都写回1
and then they both write back 1 instead of 2
基本上线程2的写入抵消了线程1的写入
because basically this write of thread 2 clobbers the fact of this write of thread 1
这是一个数据竞争
this is a data race
这是一个普遍的数据竞争
it's a general data race
导致num值与预期不符
ending up in an incorrect value of numer
正确的做法是
right the correct thing to do would be
等T1写回计算结果后，再让T2读入
to have thread 2 read this after thread 1 wrote the result of its calculation
好的
alright
就像这里
as what happens here
所以
so
数据竞争是一个问题
data races are a problem
我们该如何防范数据竞争
how can we prevent the data race in that situation
我们可以利用所谓的互斥体
we can utilize what are called mutexes
它们是线程之间的锁
they are locks between threads
它们是由操作系统提供
and they're provided by the operating system
且 libpthread 提供了很好的接口
with a nice interface by libpthread
还有信号量
there're also semaphores
可以说是一种高级的互斥锁
kind of an advanced type of mutex
这通常是操作系统课程中教授的内容
this is all stuff that is typically taught in an operating system course
我们从安全的角度快速讲一下互斥体
you're just going to very quickly touch on mutexes for the purpose of security
互斥锁基本上就是一个锁
a mutex is basically a lock
并且一次只有一个线程可以锁定它
and only a single thread can claim the lock at a time
当执行pthread_mutex_lock时
so when you do pthread_mutex_lock
将锁传递给了libpthread
you pass in that that lock to libpthread
问libpthread现在能锁它吗
and it says hey is this available
如果目前它没被锁
if no one has currently locked it
它就是我的了
it's mine
然后继续执行
and then I'll keep executing
如果已经有人锁上了
if someone has locked it
我就等它被解锁后
I'm going to wait for it to become available
我再继续执行
and then continue execution
在这段代码前后加上pthread_mutex_lock和pthread_mutex_unlock（ppt上打错了）
what this does by putting pthread_mutex_lock between this code
起到什么作用？
and pthread_mutex_lock after this code
这意味着一次只有一个线程在执行这些代码
it means that only one thread will ever be executing this code at a time
尽管这两个线程都将此作为它们的线程主函数
even though both threads have this as their thread main function
这叫做临界区
this is called a critical section
一段线程敏感代码
a section of kind of thread sensitive
需要保护的线程不安全代码
or otherwise thread unsafe code that needs to be protected
通过使用互斥锁避免数据竞争或其他线程并发性问题
from data races or other threading concurrency problems by using mutexes
看一下如何操作
let's see how it works in practice
我把它复制到这里了
I of course copied that in here
这是我们的锁
here's our lock
那是锁本身
that's the lock itself
这是对它加锁
this is us locking it
这是解锁
this is us unlocking it
已经编译了，运行它
and I compiled it and if we just run it
它什么也不打印
it never prints anything
为什么？因为num总是0
why because num is always zero
很好，我们用互斥锁解决了这个数据竞争问题
cool so we have fixed this data race through careful use of mutexes
数据竞争不是无法解决的问题
data races aren't something that just happens to you and you're hopeless
可以通过合理的编程方式阻止数据竞争
you can utilize proper programming practices to prevent data races
防止文件系统竞争也是如此
actually similarly to preventing file system races
好的
all right
我们能检测到数据竞争吗
can we detect data races
假设我们很不小心
let's say we weren't so careful
写了一堆软件
we wrote a bunch of software
到处都有竞争条件
and there're race conditions everywhere
不一定能检测到
not really
这是一个常见的课题
this is a common theme
检测数据竞争没有特效药
there isn't a magic bullet for detecting data races
是有一些工具，比如Valgrind
some tools exist so Valgrind
我们在内存错误模块中见过了Valgrind
we saw Valgrind from memory errors
在几种漏洞中都见过valgrind
we saw Valgrind through several different types of vulnerabilities
比如堆漏洞等
for heap problems and so forth
Valgrind也有检测数据竞争的工具
Valgrind also has tools to detect data races
有两个工具使用不同的方法来做这个事情
there has two different tools that use different methodologies to do the same thing
Helgrind和DRD
Helgrind and DRD
但只有在测试用例中触发相关代码 valgrind 才有用
but valgrind only works if you trigger the relevant code in your test cases
且要用它能识别的方法
in a way that it can identify
它会提示你，这里可能有数据竞争
that hey a data race could have happened here
它不是特效药
it's not a magic bullet
学术界在研究通用方法
academia the research community in general is working on magic bullets
Dr Checker是一个静态分析内核代码的系统
Dr Checker is a system that statically analyzes kernel code
可以识别各种漏洞
to identify various vulnerabilities
包括数据竞争
including data races
还有razzer和krace
and then razzer and krace
它们基本上是用随机输入来执行内核代码
they basically execute kernel code with random input
试图触发数据竞争
to try to trigger data races
但这些都不是完美的
but none of these is perfect
它还是一个问题，一个很好的例子是
right a good example that you know this problem is still a problem
最近，不确定是不是5月份，但基本是今年
is as recently as I think may but this year basically
在Linux内核的ioctl处理程序中发现了double fetch漏洞
there have been double fetch bugs in the Linux kernel in an ioctl handler
正如前面讲的
exactly in the style that I talked about just now
这些在内存中的竞争条件是个大问题
so these bugs races memory are a big deal
你们会在练习题中体会到这点
and you will experience this of course in the practice problems
好运
good luck